So earlier when we were talking about the parts of the mainframe, we looked at where the CPU and the processors are, right?
And that's called the CPC or central processor complex. We also saw where all the IO adapters are.
Did you wonder at all where all the hard drives are?
In a mainframe environment, disk storage is handled by something called direct access storage devices, commonly called DASDI.
These are big, almost mainframe sized units, stuff full of hard drives, both mechanical and solid state.
They can provide the disk storage for mainframe. They can actually provide disk storage for many mainframes, and many DASDI can be connected to a single mainframe.
So you can see there's lots of ways to connect these things.
In order to make these connections to devices like DASDI and others, we need to define the logical paths through the physical connections, so it all works.
Things are better when they work, right? The iOS CDS, which stands for the input-output configuration dataset, represents the connection between the resources and the systems that use them.
Resources are things like channels, icons, switches, control units, and other devices.
Basically, anything outside of the mainframe that we want to connect to, and the stuff inside the mainframe that we're going to use to connect to it.
So when you define an IO configuration, you provide the physical as well as the logical information about those resources.
In the mainframe, there's an input-output subsystem, or IO subsystem.
Now this controls the channel operations. That requires the information about the hardware IO configuration.
To define this, we use a program called the input-output configuration program, or IOCP.
The IOCDS is built through a series of statements. You build it brick by brick, and once you build it, the IOCDS gets stored on the SEs.
Those are those computers within the computer, and then those are picked up when the system gets powered on.
To use IOCP to build an IOCDS, you need to know about four things, and we're going to find them here.
First, you need to know what the L-Pars or partitions are that you want to work with. That's easy enough.
We've been working with those for a while now. Then you need to know about the channels.
Channels are the links between the L-Pars and the physical ports on the IO cards.
So we've got channel paths. Each one has an ID.
C-H-P-I-D, pronounced as Chippet.
We're defining a logical connection on there with the Chippet, and the channel path
exits the mainframe on the physical ID, or a P-Chid.
Control units are attached to channel paths, and they're what actually drives the device we're connecting to.
Having a dedicated control unit that is really good at handling devices like disk or tape,
means the mainframe operating system doesn't have to worry about all those deep down details.
That's a good thing.
And finally, there's the input-output device.
The thing we're actually trying to talk to, which the controlling unit is tasked with controlling.
If you know those four things, you're ready to start building an I-O-C-D-S.
So let's take a look at those statements.
There's five I-O-C-P statements.
ID, resource, chippet, control unit, and I-O device.
ID is optional, but it helps in organizing so you can find things easier later on.
You can also set the name of the local systems, the machine limits,
and the rules to be enforced by the I-O-C-P.
It comes first and can only be defined once.
Up next is resource, and this one is required.
It defines the L-par names, or if you're sharing channels between L-pars,
you can also define what's called a multiple image facility image ID, or myth ID.
So let me talk a little bit about the logical channel subsystems, or L-C-S-S.
The channel subsystem is the world that all of the channels live in, right?
The logical channel subsystem is a way of getting even more capacity for those chippets,
because now we have four logical worlds for them to live in.
Because we can create up to four of those logical channel subsystems,
we get four times the amount of chippets.
This just gives us a whole lot more options for how we can partition our resources.
You can also use this area to define a few dynamic options,
which we won't get into here.
Now, you get one resource statement, and it needs to come right after the ID statement,
if you have one.
It includes every logical partition in the configuration.
Up next is Chippet.
The Chippet statement defines all the channels on the system.
These are the logical connections between the L-par and the physical P-shit.
It defines whether that channel is dedicated, shared, reconfigurable, or spanned.
And if you're connected to Fycon switch, it also handles the assignments as well.
It also determines the availability of chippets to L-pars.
These go in after the resource and before the next two types of statements.
Number four is the control unit.
Now, this is another optional statement, but you need it if you need to connect to a device through a control unit.
And it describes three things.
First, the characteristics of the control unit.
It also defines the channel paths that the control unit is attached to, and the unit addresses that the control unit recognizes.
So basically, how I'm going to connect to the control unit, what it is I'm trying to connect to, that channel path I'm using to connect to it,
and how many unit addresses we're identifying.
Lastly, there's the I-O device.
Now, this is another optional statement, but you need it if you actually want to talk to something.
You need to have, first, the I-O device number.
You also need the device characteristics and the control units to which the device is assigned.
Now, this is all fairly abstract at this point, and it's one thing to talk about it.
Let's see what it actually happens once we start defining things with these statements.
What we're going to be doing with the following five statements is building a connection between an L-par through a chippet,
out a p-tude through a phi-con unit, and out to a 3390-DASD unit.
We'll start with the ID statement.
The symbol and everything else in the brackets is optional.
The ID here says this is an ID statement.
Message one here has the identifier of the I-O-C-D-S.
This also gets printed out on the first line of the heading of the I-O-C-P configuration reports.
It makes it easier to identify it.
Message two here has information on when it was updated, which is a pretty good idea to have that kind of stuff in there.
And you see that X all the way on the right side there?
That means that this line is continued on the line below it.
System specifies the machine limits and rules that I-O-C-P enforces for verification,
and there's also this L system and T-O-K.
These are enclosed in braces, which means that they represent alternative items.
So, they're optional.
And because we already defined system, we don't have to also define these other two.
Here's an example of a resource statement, which again identifies resources.
So, first we've got the partition, or part as it's labeled in here,
which defines the channel's subsystem ID or CSS.
Then we've got the MIF ID, which is used for sharing chippets between L-Pars.
Now, we're not doing that here, so it's not in our example, but that's where you would put it.
And then we have three L-Pars defined here.
L-P-1, L-P-2, and L-P-3.
You'll see that L-P-1 was assigned an image ID of two.
L-P-3 has an image ID of five.
And because we didn't specify one for L-P-2, it will be assigned one arbitrarily.
Here's the chippet statement.
We start out by defining channel path ID-35 in channel subsystem-1.
For the card port associated with physical channel, that's P-Chid ID-100.
We can tell it's a ficon card by the type, Equaling FC.
And it's shared between logical partitions L-P-1 and L-P-2.
Remember those from earlier?
It's all starting to come together, right?
And we can also see that this is associated with switch three E-Z.
Up next is Control Unit.
Now, what you're looking at here is the assignment of Control Unit,
number 26 Baker-0 to an IBM storage controller type 3990.
And the link address of E-Z-0 coming out of the ficon switch.
And on the main frame side, that's connected to channel path 35.
It also defines a logical address of one.
And this gives us the unit addresses of zero zero through zero fox.
Translate zero fox from hex to decimal, that's 15.
So we get 16 addresses from this statement because we start counting from zero.
So now we've defined all we need to know about the Control Unit.
One more.
Let's take a look at the I-O device statement.
So here it is, just so you know what it is.
This defines 16 device numbers, starting with address 8100.
This part right here assigns devices to Control Unit, number 26 Baker-0,
on an IBM 3990.
That 3990 Control Unit manages the device, which is a 3390.
So two very similar numbers.
And you would absolutely not be the first person in the world to mix them up.
In fact, you'd be in pretty good company.
Hi, I'm Jeff Bisty.
I believe we've met.
Lastly, it assigns a channel subsystem to L-Pars 1, 2, and 3.
This is what the L-Pars are actually going to use to connect to the channels.
So what do we actually just do?
We've got chip at 35, which is associated with P-CID 100.
And we know it's a 5-con channel, right?
We've also defined this 5-con switch with an address of 3EZ.
We've also defined the switch is connected to chip at 35 on the main frame side,
and it exits on link EZ-0.
And then it connects to the DS8886 DASDY.
Whole lot disks in there.
It's got to control unit inside of it.
That's the 3990 we defined in the last two statements.
And we're connecting to Control Unit number 26 Baker-0,
and it's giving us addresses 8100 through 8100 Fox.
That was exhausting.
I know.
It wasn't exactly plug and play.
But the reason we basically define every little thing
and how every little thing connects to every other little thing
is because there needs to be absolutely no two ways
of interpreting these definitions.
It's also actually kind of nice,
because in this document, in this series of statements,
the entire IO ecosystem is defined.
So you can read through one of these and get an extremely clear picture
of how your addresses are defined,
what they're connected to, which L parts get access to them,
everything you could possibly want to know about your devices.
And it's not easy at first.
Trust me.
I know we just hit you with a lot,
but this is just one of those things where you get to walk into a job interview and say,
yeah, I was just building a practice IODF config based on an online mainframe course I was taking,
and that's going to earn you some major points.